Guide to the Joe Schaumburger Papers, 1954-1986 and undated RL.11379
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joe Schaumburger papers
1954-1986 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11379
0.2 Linear Feet
Joe Schaumburger's collection of correspondence and early writings by Lin Carter.
Biographical / Historical
This collection from the estate of science fiction author and editor Joe Schaumburger (1930-2011) sheds light on the personal life of prolific science fiction writer Lin Carter. Schaumburger became close to Carter in 1948, about a year after Carter's letters and poems began appearing in science fiction magazines. They bonded over their shared passion for science fiction, ultimately working together as writers at Prentice-Hall. Schaumburger finished his career at Daw Books where he was managing editor.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Joe Schaumburger Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchase in 2017.
Related Materials
Rubenstein Library also holds the Lin Carter Papers.
Collection Overview
This archive mostly shows Carter's humorous side and includes 18 different original drawings that most likely date to the late 1950s. Includes Carter's illustrated creation of the "Genito-Urinary Book Club" that mocks get-rich-quick schemes and self-help books. It involves becoming a member of the "Royal Order of the Purple Bladder" and buying books such as "How to Cash in on Your Kidney Stones".
Other highlights include a number of inscribed greeting cards and invitations, apparently unpublished book reviews and humor essays, original handwritten poetry and a rare issue of Carter's fanzine, The Saturday Evening Toad, issued with Schaumburger in 1957.
There are also several letters between Schaumburger and Carter, including a moving letter from Carter in his final years where he describes his dire financial straits and inability to get medical care because he cannot afford it.
- Books for the Schaumb, undated (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Lin Carter's book recommendations for Schaumburger
- Correspondence: Holiday cards and postcards with Lin Carter, 1970-1986, undated (Box 1)
  Holiday cards and general correspondence between Lin Carter and Schaumburger
- Correspondence: Letters to/from Lin Carter, 1962-1983 (Box 1)
  Personal correspondence and science fiction correspondence, where Carter and Schaumburger write as characters
- Correspondence: Letter from William Brady, M.D. (Box 1)
  Letter trying to sell health book
- Drawings of "Schomb" (Box 1)
  Drawings that mainly portray "Schomb", but also other related characters and events
- Genito-Urinary Inc., undated (Box 1)
  Satirical series of letters from "Genito-Urinary inc." trying to sell books, dynamics
- Halloween at Cartermanse Invitations, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  Invitations to themed halloween parties at Lin Carter's house
- Letters to the Editor, undated (Box 1)
  From the files of FATE Magazine. Fictional correspondence between editor and writer
- Lin Carter's Writing Secrets, 1977 (Box 1)
- Linzifoos Sweepstakes, undated (Box 1)
  Letters from "Howard D. Fubble" about the Linzifoos Sweepstakes
- The Lorelei, 1957 (Box 1)
  Translated from the German of Heinrich Heine by Carter and Schaumburger
- Miscellaneous Lin Carter drafts, 1954, undated (Box 1)
- Route Marchin', undated (Box 1)
  Poem
- The Royal Order of the Purple Bladder, undated (Box 1)
  Fictional letter from "Oscar Overunder" about joining the Royal Order of the Purple Bladder
- The Saturday Evening Toad, 1957 Aug. (Box 1)
  no. 2 of Lin Carter's magazine
- Science Fiction Membership Cards, 1954 and 1965 (Box 1)